Finding Aid to the Mobilization Against AIDS Records, 1984-1995
UCSF Library and Center for Knowledge Management, Archives and Special Collections
Mobilization Against AIDS records,
1984-1995
MSS 95-03
Mobilization Against Aids
Number of containers: 3 cartons Linear feet: 3.75
The UCSF Library and Center for Knowledge Management, Archives and Special Collections University of California, San Francisco 530 Parnassus Avenue San Francisco, CA 94143-0840 Phone: (415) 476-8112 Fax: (415) 476-4653 Email: http://www.library.ucsf.edu/collres/archives/contactform.html URL: http://www.library.ucsf.edu/collres/archives/
This collection documents the founding, administration and work of the Mobilization Against AIDS also known as the MOB. MOB was primarily a lobbying organization working against anti-AIDS initiatives and governmental policies, promoting the testing of new AIDS Drugs, and generally drawing attention to the AIDS epidemic around the world. They are best known for their AIDS Dance-a-thon fundraiser and the International AIDS Candlelight Vigil outreach activity.
Information for Researchers
Access
Collection is open for research.
Alternate Forms Available
There are no alternate forms of this collection.
Separated Material
None
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
AIDS (Disease)--California--San Francisco; AIDS (Disease)--Political aspects--United States; AIDS (Disease)--Research--Government policy; AIDS (Disease)--Social aspects--California--San Francisco Bay Area; AIDS activists--United States; Social action--United States; Mobilization Against AIDS (organization)
Administrative Information
Acquisition Information
The Mobilization Against AIDS Records were donated to the University by Ben Carlson for the Mobilization Against AIDS in 1995.
System of Arrangement
Arranged to the folder level.
Organizational History
The Mobilization Against AIDS is a California-based national advocacy and lobbying organization that works to safeguard civil rights and to assure adequate treatment for all HIV-infected individuals. The Mobilization was formed in San Francisco in 1984 as a non-partisan activist organization. The organization was founded on the positive energy generated from the March for Lesbian and Gay Rights at the National Democratic Convention. It is one of the oldest AIDS activist groups in the world, having been founded just three years after AIDS was identified.
The Mobilization's first priority was the defeat of the early civil rights attacks on people with AIDS, and then on increasing the funding for research on AIDS. This included advocating for a focused response to the AIDS epidemic from the federal government, and expanded to concerns over access to treatment, drug trials, drug approval processes, and drug costs.
MOB was a central player in the massive campaigns that succeeded in defeating the LaRouche AIDS Quarantine Initiatives in 1986 and 1988, and the Dannemeyer AIDS Initiative in 1988. In 1990 federal legislation explicitly prohibited discrimination against people with AIDS. As a direct lobbying group, the Mobilization organizes staff and volunteers to meet with federal officials and legislators. This has led to the development of long-term relationships with congressional representatives, especially those on the House of Representatives Budget and Appropriations Committees. Between 1984 and 1990 federal AIDS spending went from $85 million to over $1.8 billion, partially as a result of MOB lobbying efforts. The MOB also assists interested citizens in writing and visiting key federal officials and legislators, including the creation of kits that include sample letters and other tips.
Another major project has been organizing the International Candlelight Memorial. Since 1984, the event has become the world's largest simultaneous observance honoring the memory of AIDS victims and demonstrating support for people living with AIDS (PWA's). Memorials have taken place in over 220 cities in 35 countries. Events are arranged locally with support from the Mobilization, including supplying sample posters, letters to dignitaries, and providing logistical tips.
They have also worked with other agencies for more effective lobbying efforts. The Mobilization has received the majority of its funding from the AIDS Walkathon and the AIDS Dance-a-thon with the remainder coming from individual donations.
Scope and Content of Collection
This collection documents the founding, administration and work of the Mobilization Against AIDS also known as the MOB. The MOB is primarily a lobbying organization working against anti-AIDS initiatives and government policies, promoting the testing of new AIDS Drugs, and generally drawing attention to the AIDS epidemic around the world. It is also an outreach organization. MOB worked to bring public understanding and support to the HIV-positive community, and to champion AIDS as an issue of concern to all.
Both board and staff meeting minutes are included in the administrative records. Besides a number of smaller fundraising events, their primary event was the Annual AIDS Dance-a-thon. This fundraiser, which was held between 1987 and 1996, attracted the endorsement of celebrities such as Madonna, and provided monies not just to MOB, but to a number of other AIDS Organizations such as the San Francisco AIDS Foundation and Instituto Familiar de la Raza. Outreach activities and programs ranged from Town Hall meetings to the International AIDS Candlelight Vigil, an outreach activity which grew from a local event into a truly worldwide night of commemoration. The MOB's main activity, however, was working against the early homophobic anti-AIDS initiatives, lobbying the government for increased AIDS funding, and working for the release of better AIDS drugs. The MOB staff and board not only lobbied, but also organized "Lobbying Teams" and "Lobbying Days" to bring ordinary citizens into the movement and increase the pressure on the politicians. Flyers for events, a MOB button and handkerchief, along with a few photographs, are also included in the collection.
The Collection is divided into three series: Series 1: Founding, Board, and Administrative Files; Series 2: Fundraising, Program, and Organizational Files; Series 3: Publicity/Publications/Ephemera.
Container List
- Founding, Board, and Administrative Files, 1984-1995; Series 1; 50 Folders: Carton 1 Folders 1/1-1/50
  This series contains documents relating to the founding of the Mobilization Against AIDS, as well as board of directors minutes and other administrative files including staff meeting minutes, correspondence, and financial documents.
  - MAA History, 1991 (Carton 1, Folder 1)
  - Creation of Mobilization, December 1984 (Carton 1, Folder 2)
  - Strategy and Foundation Conference (including John Wahl's notes, etc.), March 29-31, 1985 (Carton 1, Folder 3)
  - Mobilization Conference Minutes, March 30-31, 1985 (Carton 1, Folder 4)
  - Steering Committee Minutes, 1985 (Carton 1, Folder 5)
  - Town Hall, General and Steering Committee - Reports, Minutes, Notes, 1985 (Carton 1, Folder 6)
  - Board/Working Committee Minutes, 1986 (Carton 1, Folder 7)
  - Steering Committee - Notes and Minutes, 1988 (Carton 1, Folder 8)
  - Board Meetings (Carton 1, Folder 9-18)
    - January 1989 (Carton 1, Folder 9)
    - April 1989 (Carton 1, Folder 10)
    - July 1989 (Carton 1, Folder 11)
    - 1990 (Carton 1, Folder 12)
    - January, March, July, September, November 1991 (Carton 1, Folder 13)
    - January-July 1992 (Carton 1, Folder 14)
    - Memo, October 1992 (Carton 1, Folder 15)
    - September-November 1992 (Carton 1, Folder 16)
    - 1993 (Carton 1, Folder 17)
    - 1994-1995 (Carton 1, Folder 18)
  - Board and Committee Members - including resignations, 1985; 1993,; undated (Carton 1, Folder 19)
  - Board Committees, 1993 (Carton 1, Folder 20)
  - Board/Staff Retreat, January 1992 (Carton 1, Folder 21)
  - Board/Staff Meeting #2, June 1992 (Carton 1, Folder 22)
  - Staff Meetings (Carton 1, Folder 23-25)
    - Minutes and Memos, 1992 (Carton 1, Folder 23)
    - Notes - Preliminary, 1993 (Carton 1, Folder 24)
    - Official Minutes, 1993-94 (Carton 1, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence (Carton 1, Folder 26-43)
    - Paul Boneberg, 1985-1992 (Carton 1, Folder 26)
    - Barbara Boxer, 1986-1990 (Carton 1, Folder 27)
    - Nancy Pelosi, 1993-1995 (Carton 1, Folder 28)
    - President Ronald Regan (draft), 1987 (Carton 1, Folder 29)
    - John E. Wahl, 1980-1986; undated (Carton 1, Folder 30)
    - Political Correspondence (Carton 1, Folder 31-33)
      - 1985 (Carton 1, Folder 31)
      - 1989 (Carton 1, Folder 32)
      - 1992,1995 (Carton 1, Folder 33)
    - Dance-a-thon, 1987-1990 (Carton 1, Folder 34)
    - From Individuals, 1989 (Carton 1, Folder 35)
    - Local HIV/AIDS CBO - Re: Problems, 1994 (Carton 1, Folder 36)
    - From Mayors Office - Re: Citizens Advocating Emergency AIDS Relief (CAEAR) Coalition, 1995 (Carton 1, Folder 37)
    - General Correspondence (Carton 1, Folder 38-39)
      - 1985-1994 (Carton 1, Folder 38)
      - 1993-1995 (Carton 1, Folder 39)
    - Interoffice Memos (Carton 1, Folder 40-43)
      - July-August 1992 (Folder 40)
      - October-December 1992 (Carton 1, Folder 41)
      - January-December 1993 (Carton 1, Folder 42)
      - February-November 1994 (Carton 1, Folder 43)
  - Personnel Committee/Office Structure, 1985-1992 (Carton 1, Folder 44)
  - Office Policy, 1990-1992; undated (Carton 1, Folder 45)
  - Financial Documents (Carton 1, Folder 46-50)
    - Finance Committee Meeting, September, 1989 (Carton 1, Folder 46)
    - Reports, 1990; 1992 (Carton 1, Folder 47)
    - MAA-PAC - A Federal Election Campaign, 1992-1993 (Carton 1, Folder 48)
    - Consultants Report - Finance/Development, 1993 (Carton 1, Folder 49)
    - 1991-1992 Audit, May, 1994 (Carton 1, Folder 50)
- Fundraising, Program, and Organizational Files, 1985-1995; Series 2; 94 Folders: Carton 2 Folders 2/1-2/74; Carton 3 Folders 3/1-3/20
  This series contains information on a variety of programs, both outreach and fundraising. This includes information on the Mobilization Against AIDS' two major events: The annual Dance-a-thon, which was promoted by Madonna (among others), and served as their major fundraiser; and the Candlelight Vigil, which became a very successful international outreach event. Also documented in this series are the Mobilization's lobbying efforts, including the creation of "Lobby Teams," "Lobby Day" as a part of the 1992 March on Washington, several petition drives, as well as work against a number of anti-gay propositions, and advocacy for increased AIDS funding. There is also a small amount of material on a number of other AIDS agencies that worked with the Mobilization.
  - Development and Fundraising Events (Carton 2, Folder 1-27)
    - Membership Fundraising Letters, 1992-1993 (Carton 2, Folder 1)
    - Development Committee (Carton 2, Folder 2-3)
      - October 1992 - February 1993 (Carton 2, Folder 2)
      - March-June 1993 (Carton 2, Folder 3)
    - Development Director - Info. Packet, 1992 (Carton 2, Folder 4)
    - Fundraising Events, 1984-1989; 1995 (Carton 2, Folder 5-27)
      - April Harvest, Leola Jones, & others, 1985 (Carton 2, Folder 5)
      - Death Valley Rose Challenge, 1985 (Carton 2, Folder 6)
      - 2nd Wave/Project Hope, 1988-1989 (Carton 2, Folder 7)
      - East Bay Board Fundraising Event, 1991 (Carton 2, Folder 8)
      - SF Board Cocktail Party - Fundraiser, 1991; undated (Carton 2, Folder 9)
      - Macy's Passport 92, 1992 (Carton 2, Folder 10)
      - Indecent Materials (Carton 2, Folder 11-12)
        - Event, 1994 (Carton 2, Folder 11)
        - Script (copyright 1990), 1994 (Carton 2, Folder 12)
      - Yours in the Struggle: A Tribute to Reggie Williams, February 1994 (Carton 2, Folder 13)
      - Telephone Solicitation Project (TSP), undated (Carton 2, Folder 14)
      - Dance-a-thon (Carton 2, Folder 15-27)
        - 1987 (Carton 2, Folder 15)
        - 1988 (Carton 2, Folder 16)
        - Contract with San Francisco AIDS Foundation (SFAF), 1992 (Carton 2, Folder 17)
        - 1993 (Carton 2, Folder 18)
        - Contracts - Miller, Zeichik, and Associates (MZA) and SFAF [1994], 1993-1994 (Carton 2, Folder 19)
        - American Indian AIDS Institute [1994], 1993-1994 (Carton 2, Folder 20)
        - GAPA Community HIV Project [1994], 1993-1994 (Carton 2, Folder 21)
        - HIV Prevention Project [1994], 1993-1994 (Carton 2, Folder 22)
        - Instituto Familiar de la Raza [1994], 1993-1994 (Carton 2, Folder 23)
        - Project Inform [1994], 1993-1994 (Carton 2, Folder 24)
        - San Francisco Black Coalition on AIDS [1994], 1993-1994 (Carton 2, Folder 25)
        - 1994 (Carton 2, Folder 26)
        - 1990,1995 (Carton 2, Folder 27)
  - Articles/Speeches by Paul Boneberg, 1987-1991 (Carton 2, Folder 28)
  - Research and Documentation Committee, 1985 (Carton 2, Folder 29)
  - People with AIDS/People with ARC (PWA/PWARC) Caucus, 1985 (Carton 2, Folder 30)
  - Goals and Programs, 1989-1991 (Carton 2, Folder 31)
  - Programs, Carton 2 Folder 32 - Carton 3 Folder 4
    - Candlelight Memorials/Vigils (Carton 2, Folder 32-35)
      - 1985-1995 (Carton 2, Folder 32)
      - Capp Street Foundation, 1987 (Carton 2, Folder 33)
      - Booklets, 1990-1992 (Carton 2, Folder 34)
      - Clippings, 1986-1989 (Carton 2, Folder 35)
    - Condom Promotion, 1987 (Carton 2, Folder 36)
    - The Hour Brigade, 1985-1987 (Carton 2, Folder 37)
    - MAA Library, 1985; undated (Carton 2, Folder 38)
    - Antibody Testing Opinions, 1988 (Carton 2, Folder 39)
    - American Medical Association Campaign, 1985 (Carton 2, Folder 40)
    - Press Releases, 1984-1995 (Carton 2, Folder 41)
    - Legislative Activities (Carton 2, Folder 42-59)
      - Federal AIDS Hearings, 1985 (Carton 2, Folder 42)
      - State, 1985-1986 (Carton 2, Folder 43)
      - Homophobic Propaganda, 1986 (Carton 2, Folder 44)
      - LaRouche Initiative - Non-Compliance Project, 1986 (Carton 2, Folder 45)
      - LaRouche Quarantine Initiative, 1986 (Carton 2, Folder 46)
      - California Mandatory Testing Bills (Doolittle S.B. 1000-10008), 1987 (Carton 2, Folder 47)
      - No on Prop. 102 and LaRouche Campaign - Newsclippings, 1988 (Carton 2, Folder 48)
      - Prop. 192 - Dannemeyer, 1988 (Carton 2, Folder 49)
      - San Francisco Ballot Initiatives, 1985; 1989 (Carton 2, Folder 50)
      - Updates - Legi-Tech Reports & Bills, 1985-1988 (Carton 2, Folder 51)
      - Just Sign It! Campaign, 1992 (Carton 2, Folder 52)
      - Federal (Carton 2, Folder 53-54)
        - 1983-1986 (Carton 2, Folder 53)
        - 1993 (Carton 2, Folder 54)
      - National AIDS Lobby Day, 1992 (Carton 2, Folder 55)
      - Federal AIDS Funding, 1991-1992 (Carton 2, Folder 56)
      - Ryan White Care Act, 1993-1995 (Carton 2, Folder 57)
      - Lobby Teams (Carton 2, Folder 58-59)
        - 1990-1991 (Carton 2, Folder 58)
        - Lobby Team 1992, 1992-1993 (Carton 2, Folder 59)
    - International Programs, 1992 (Carton 2, Folder 60)
    - 1990 Sixth International AIDS Conference - Boycott, 1989-1990 (Carton 2, Folder 61)
    - HIV/AIDS Unity March (Carton 2, Folder 62-63)
      - Planning Notes and Materials, March 1990 (Carton 2, Folder 62)
      - Press Coverage, 1990 (Carton 2, Folder 63)
    - Republican Convention Action, 1988 (Carton 2, Folder 64)
    - Presidential Debates, 1992 (Carton 2, Folder 65)
    - Houston Republican Convention, 1992 (Carton 2, Folder 66)
    - March on Washington, 1987 (Carton 2, Folder 67)
    - March on Washington Lobby Days, 1993 (Carton 2, Folder 68)
    - Worlds AIDS Day Protest/Arrests, 1989 (Carton 2, Folder 69)
    - "Moon Shot" Petition, 1986 (Carton 2, Folder 70)
    - KQED Protest - Press Coverage, 1986 (Carton 2, Folder 71)
    - Delta Airlines Boycott, 1989 (Carton 2, Folder 72)
    - March on Sacramento, 1988 (Carton 2, Folder 73)
    - Burroughs Wellcome - Boycott - Advisory Board, 1989; 1993-1995 (Carton 2, Folder 74)
    - Call for Resignation of Kristine Gebbie - National AIDS Policy Coordinator, 1994 (Carton 3, Folder 1)
    - 1990 Year in Review Compendium, 1990-1991 (Carton 3, Folder 2)
    - 1992 Year in Review (Carton 3, Folder 3)
    - Loose Documents - handwritten notes, forms, etc., 1984-1992 (Carton 3, Folder 4)
  - Seattle and Phoenix Chapters of MAA, 1985-1986 (Carton 3, Folder 5)
  - "Packet of Materials for Linus Pauling", 1985 (Carton 3, Folder 6)
  - Other Organizations/Cooperation (Carton 3, Folder 7-20)
    - AIDS Action Council - TB/HIV, 1992 (Carton 3, Folder 7)
    - Asian AIDS Project, 1994-1995 (Carton 3, Folder 8)
    - Committee to Preserve our Sexual Liberties, 1984; undated (Carton 3, Folder 9)
    - Health and Human Services (HHS) HIV Prevention Working Group, 1993; 1995 (Carton 3, Folder 10)
    - Joint Task Force on the HIV Epidemic - SF, 1993-1994 (Carton 3, Folder 11)
    - LIFE AIDS Lobby - Lobby for Individual Freedom & Equality, 1989 (Carton 3, Folder 12)
    - National Association of People with AIDS (NAPWA), 1995 (Carton 3, Folder 13)
    - PANT - Pentamidine Advocates for Necessary Treatment, 1989 (Carton 3, Folder 14)
    - People with AIDS Coalition, 1995 (Carton 3, Folder 15)
    - San Francisco AIDS Foundation, 1993-1995 (Carton 3, Folder 16)
    - San Francisco AIDS Foundation - Prevention Roundtable, 1992 (Carton 3, Folder 17)
    - San Francisco Public Policy Working Group, 1994-1995 (Carton 3, Folder 18)
    - Visual AIDS - Posters, 1994 (Carton 3, Folder 19)
    - Other Organizations - includes religious organizations, 1984-1985; undated (Carton 3, Folder 20)
- Publicity/Publications/Ephemera, 1985-1995; Series 3; 19 Folders: Carton 3 Folders 3/21-3/39
  This series contains flyers for Mobilization Against AIDS events, clippings and other materials related to media coverage of events and programs. This includes the Mobilization's communications and press plan. There are also a scattering of Mobilization newsletters and more formal publications such as Action Alert and AIDSwatch. The final materials in this series are several buttons related to Mobilization events and campaigns, and a small amount of photographs from various events.
  - Media and Publicity (Carton 3, Folder 21-34)
    - Flyers (Carton 3, Folder 21-25)
      - 1985 (Carton 3, Folder 21)
      - 1987 (Carton 3, Folder 22)
      - 1988 (Carton 3, Folder 23)
      - 1989 (Carton 3, Folder 24)
      - undated (Carton 3, Folder 25)
    - Media Coverage (Carton 3, Folder 26-31)
      - 1984-1985 (Carton 3, Folder 26)
      - 1986-1987 (Carton 3, Folder 27)
      - 1988 (Carton 3, Folder 28)
      - 1989 (Carton 3, Folder 29)
      - 1990-1991 (Carton 3, Folder 30)
      - 1995 (Carton 3, Folder 31)
    - Review of Media, 1985 (Carton 3, Folder 32)
    - Communications and Press Plan, 1992 (Carton 3, Folder 33)
    - Miscellaneous MAA Advertising and Media Criticism, 1994; undated (Carton 3, Folder 34)
  - Publications (Carton 3, Folder 35-37)
    - Newsletters - Communications, 1985 (Carton 3, Folder 35)
    - Action Alert, 1989-1995 (Carton 3, Folder 36)
    - AIDSwatch, 1993-199? (Carton 2, Folder 37)
  - MAA Buttons & Handkerchief, 1988; 1991,; 1992,; undated (Carton 3, Folder 38)
  - Photographs, 1985-1988; 1991-1992 (Carton 3, Folder 39)